<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../bodley-msDesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../bodley-msDesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_1">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>OXFORD ARMENIAN MANUSCRIPTS CATALOGUE ONLINE</title>
            <funder>JISC-??-</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bodleian Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Special Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bodleian Library</addrLine>
                  <street>Broad Street</street>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/libraries/collections">Bodleian Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>oriental@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Arm_b_1</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Armenian</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>Oxford University</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection type="main">Oriental Manuscripts </collection>
                  <idno>MS. Arm. b. 1</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>Old fly-leaves</summary>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item1" n="1">
                     <locus>f. 1</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains Matt XV.14-31, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. Size 10.125" by 5.625". Text originally 10.25" by 8.25", in two colums of 21 lines each. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir. Not later than the 11th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 3.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item2" n="2">
                     <locus>f. 2</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains Matt. XXV. 45 - XXVI. 17, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. Size 11.875" by 8.375". Text originally 10.5" by 9", in two columns of 19 lines each. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir, with capitals on the verso written in yellow ink. Not later than the 11th cent. Taken from MS. Marsh 467.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item3" n="3">
                     <locus>f. 3</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains Matt. XXVI. 34-45, with marignal Eusebian section-numbers.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. Size 12.75" by 9". Text originally 11" by 7.5", in two columns of 19 lines each. Written on both sides in large elegant Erkat'agir. Not later than the 11th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. d. 2.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item4" n="4">
                     <locus>f. 4</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains parts ot Mark VIII. 38 - IX. 6, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. A leaf cut across into halves, between which about 1.5" has been lost: the left-hand side of the upper half is also wanting. Size, including the interval of paper between the halves, 15.875" by 10.75". Text originally 11.25" by 7.25", in two clumns of 16 lines each. Written on both sides in large Erkat'agir. Not later than the 11th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 5.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item5" n="5">
                     <locus>f. 5</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains Luke VII. 19-29, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. Size 14.75" by 9.5". Text 11.625" by 8.25" in two columns of 19 lines each. Written on both sides in large and very neat Erkat'agir. Apparently not later than the 10th cent. Taken from MS. Marsh 128.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item6" n="6">
                     <locus>f. 6</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">The lower part of a leaf, containin on the recto Luke VIII. 16, 18, 19, and on the verso Luke VIII. 21, 22, 24.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum, much stained. Size 6.75" by 10.625". Text originally 10.5" by 7.75", in two columns of 7 lines each (originally 17), with large margins. Not later than the 10th cent. Taken from the cover of MS. Arm. e. 3.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item7" n="7">
                     <locus>f. 7</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Two fragments of different MSS. The first fragment contains Luke VIII. 51, 54-56; the second Luke XXI. 4, 6, 7, 9, 12, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. The upper part of one leaf, and the lower part of another. Size 5.625" by 5.625", and 5.625" by 8". TExt, in two columns, the first fragment having 8 lines left, the second 6. Written on both sides in large Erkat'agir. Not later than the 11th cent. Taken from MS. Marsh 17.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item8" n="9">
                     <locus>f. 8</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">The fragments formed part of the same copy of the Gispels: they contain, of course with some deficiencies, the passages Luke IX. 1-12, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers, and 42-57.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment very much stained. Two leaves. Size, 10" by 7" and 10.375" by 7". TExt originally 10.375" by 7", in two columns, originally of 20 lines each, but now of 18 lines in the first fragment and 17 in the second. Written on boths sides in large Erkat'agir. Not later than the 11th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 7.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item9" n="11">
                     <locus>f. 10</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains part of the Ritual, viz. a portion of the Canon of the third day of the Burial of a priest; parts of these lessons and prayers are not in the printed editions.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum. A sheet of two leaves, each with the top, bottom, and outer side mutilated. Size, 6.875" by 9.75" (breadth of second leaf 5.25"). Text in two columns of 18 lines each. Written in neat Erkat'agir, with occasional rubrication. Content cf. ed, Venice, 1831, pp. 476 - 477. Apparently of the 13th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 6.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item10" n="12">
                     <locus>f. 12</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains the latter part of the Canon of the Benediction of cereals, harvest, and vintage, and nearly all the Prayer in time of drought (Վասն Երաշտութեան).</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment, soiled. Size, 10.5" by 6.75". Text (partly cut off down each side) in two columns: those on the recto contain parts of 26 lines, with possible traces of a 27th; those on the verso parts or traces of 25 lines. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir. Content cf. ed. Ven. pp. 700-701, 706. Apparently of the 12th century. Taken from MS. Marsh 646.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item11" n="13">
                     <locus>f. 13</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Belonging to a lectionary for festivals (Տօնական), it contains on the recto the latter part of Matt. XXIII.37-39, followed by the heading of the day of commemoration of the council of Ephesus on the 30th of Arats (=Feb. 18) followed ny the historical discourse of Philoxenus, bishop of Mabug (Membij in Syria), on the same council, in framgents.</title>
                     <title xml:lang="hy">Երանելւոյն Փիղիքսիանոսի Նաբուքայ եպիսկապոսի (sic) Պատճառք ժողովոյն …յ եւ Եփեսոսի քակտոիմն Նստորի (sic) …</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. Size, 7" by 10.375". Text in two columns (mutilated at top and bottom): those on th recto contain respectively 20 lines (with a possible trace of another) and 26 lines; those on the verso 25 and 24. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir, with 7 lines in small Bolorgir-uncials. Content cf. Zarbhanalian's "Catal. des anciennes traductions Arméniennes, Venice, 1889, p. 734. Apparently of the 12th century. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 9.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item12" n="14">
                     <locus>f. 14</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Belonged to a Lectionary for festivals (Տօնական), and contains the last lines of the 42nd lesson and the beginning of the homily of Theodotus, bishop of Ancyra, on the Nativity of Christ.</title>
                     <title xml:lang="xcl-Latn-x-hmb">ԽԲ. Թեոդոտոսի եպիսկոպոսի Անկիւրա [խաւսք ի] ծնունդն տ՟ն մերոյ յ՟ի ք՟ի …</title>
                     <incipit>Պայ]ծար եւ հրաշափառ է մերձա[կայ] տաւնիս խորհուրդ …</incipit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. A leaf cut acriss into halves, between which 0.75" or so has been lost. Size (including the interval of paper between the halves), 21.25" by 13.5". Text (a few letters of each line cut off down the inner side of the inner column), in two columns of (at present) 42 lines each. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir, with a large rose-coloured and light-green arabesque, and occasional red and black striped ornamentation occupying an entire line. According to Zarbhanalian (p. 470), the homily is ascribed to Theodoros or Theodosius in MSS. preserved in the library of San Lazaro, VEnice, but the reading of Gallandus (Bibl. Patr. ix. p. 440) agrees with our fragment. Apparently of the 11th or 12th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. d. 1.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item13" n="15">
                     <locus>f. 15</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains a portion of the XVIth (according to the Greek text, XXth) of the Lesser Monastic Rules (called in the Armenian Հարցողաց գիրք) of St. Basil, but part of the second page is almost or quite illegible.</title>
                     
                     <incipit>ընդունին. եւ ոչ զգ[ուշա]նասն ասդի փափ[կու]թեան. պատրաստ լեր …</incipit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. Size, 9.375" by 6.875". Text in two columns of 15 lines each, the top and inner side of the inner column being cut off. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir. Apparently from the 12th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 9.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item14" n="16">
                     <locus>f. 16</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">The lower part of a leaf: on the first page, after these words of the end of some ascetic treatise, հանդերձեալքս, եւ բազում փութոյ արժանաւորք այժմուքս, follows the garbled title: Վասն եղբայրսիրու - On brotherly love. On the verso: առաքինութեամբ: ԻԲ. Աղաւթք առա՟ծ վասն յառաքինութեան յառաջադիմութեան - XXII. Prayer to God for progress in virtue.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. Size, 6.875" by 9.25". Text in two columns of (at present) t lines each, with large margins, but with the inner half of the inner columns cut off. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir. Apparently 13th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. d. 2.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item15" n="17">
                     <locus>f.</locus>
                     <author>Evagrius, Ponticus, <date calendar="#Gregorian" from="0345" to="0399">345?-399</date>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains 4 fragments of the works of Evagrius of Pontus.</title>
                     <title xml:lang="hy">a) Եւագրեայ Բան խրատու. Զերախայրին կալոյ իմոյ …; b) Եւագրեայ Առ մարտիրոսն.; c) Նորին Եւագրեայ .Եթէ ունիցիս ընդ քեւ եղբարս …; d) Հաւատք որ ի Նիկիայ</title>
                     <incipit>a) … գաւազանք հեզոց բղխեսցեն ընկոյզ …; b) … ք՟ս տուր ինձ համարձակութիւն ընդ սուրբսն քո … Վասն Յարութեան. Յարութեանն ք՟ի երկրպագեսցուք …; c) … սցի ի խուողէ անտի, կամ ի սպանողէ անտի … Ես Պաւղին այսպէս փառաւորեալ որպէս ընկալայ ի հարցն, հաւատամ …; d) … սուրբ կատարեալ. պբարեխաւս առանց առնելոյ …</incipit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. Four leaves. Size, about 7.125" by 5.625". Text, about 5" by 3.5", of 18 lines to the page. Written on both sides in small and neat Erkat'agir, with large initials in gold over rose-colour. Apparently of the 13th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 4.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item16" n="21">
                     <locus>f. 21</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">[Unidentified content]</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. Size, 3.625" square. Text, in two columns (most of the inner colum being cut away) of (at present) 8 lines each, and with apparent traces of a 9th lines. Written on one side in Erkat'agir, with rubriatcion. The bottom of a leaf, only partially legible. Apparently of the 12th cent. Taken from MSS. Arm. g. 1. Across it is written in a late hand: ես տ՟ր մաթիոս֊տվի այս տըրտ՟ն. բարսեղ աբեղին. ժամուց - "I Sir Mathios gave this hour's book to Barseł the monk".</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item17" n="22">
                     <locus>f. 22</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">A leaf of the Gospels containt Marl X. 15-38, with marginal Eusebian section-numbers, and with corresponding harmonies at the bottom of the page.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum. Size, 14.5" by 11". Text, 11.625" by 8.25", in two columns o 28 lines each. Written on both sides in Erkat'agir. Probably of the 10th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. d. 8.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item18" n="23">
                     <locus>f. 23</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">A leaf of a Ritual, containt part of the service for the Burial of a priest.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment. Size, 12.875" by 9.5". Text, mutilated at top, nearly the same, in two columns of 26 or 27 lines. Written on both sides in large Erkat'agir. for the text, and small or square Erkat'agir for the titles or rubrics. Probably of the 13th cent. Taken from MS. Arm. d. 8.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item19" n="24">
                     <locus>f. 24</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Contains portions of miral treatises.</title>
                     
                     <incipit>… նամանելի. այղ ոչ բերել առաքինաբար … ութեանն. յիշայ զտ՟րն. զի ի ճոխութե [անաղ] քատացաւ վասն մեր. եթե անզգամ զքեզ …</incipit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum. Size, about 8.25" by 6" each. Text (originally about 9.25" by 6"), about 7.25" by 5.25", in from 14 to 15 lines (wth apparent trace of a 16th), but every page has lost on or more lines. Written on both sides in medum-sized Erkat'agir. Two folios. Probably of the 12th cent. Taken from MS. Marsh 85.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item20" n="26">
                     <locus>f. 26</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">a) Fragment of a commentary on Is.XL.8, discoursing the superior excellence of the soul as compared to the body; b) Two extracts from Lives of Fathers; c) Fragment of some unknwon commentary, in which the Temptation of Jesus in the wilderness is spoken of.</title>
                     <incipit>a) և տես զլոիծեալսն և ահ[ա ոչ] խոտ միայն այլ և մոխիր տեսանես … ; b) … յայլ թգ՟ր հը[րեշտակ ի քաղաքն] ի մի յաւուրց …; c) … այնոքիկ իցեն. ոչ միայն այն զոր խօսեցաւ ըբդ մվ՟ի և ընդ այլս ….</incipit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Two oalimpsest sheets of two folios each. Size of each leaf, about 7" by 4.875". The under text us only in very slight part decipherable, but was written in very small square Erkat'agir of about the 11th or 12th cent., and belonged to a liturgical book. The upper text measures about 6.375" by 4.375", in from 20 to 26 lines - the top line or two in the second sheet being partly or entirely cut away. It is written in cursive bolorgir of about the 14th cent., with many abbreviations and monograms and with traces of rubrication. Taken from MS. Arm. e. 2.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item21" n="28">
                     <locus>f. 30</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Fragments of a lectionary.</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Parchment, much browned abd stained. Size, 6.25" by 8.75". Text, in two columns, but curtailed on all sides, each at present containing only four lines. Writing, in large square Erkat'agir of 10the or 11th cent. Contains: the Lessons of Wednesday of the second week of Lent, i.e. on recto 1st col., Exod.II.22, and Joel II.1; 2nd col., Joel II.2-4l on verso, 1st col., Joel II.6-7; 2nd col., Joel II.9-11. Before this folio was mutilated and used as a fly-leaf, a good hand, perhaps of the 15th cent., wrote out on the recto a list of saints whose days are kept from the 15th to the 19th of some month. One discerns the names of SS. Leontios, Nerses, Polycarp, Hilary the wonder worker, Kirakos, Eugenia, and others. Later hans have also covered th verso with rude writing. Taken from MS. Arm .f. 6.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item22" n="29">
                     <locus>f. 30</locus>
                     <author>John Chrysostom, Saint, <date calendar="#Gregorian" from="0407">d. 407</date>
                     </author>
                     <title xml:lang="en">(Verso:) End of a homily; (Recto:) Beginning of the Homily of John Chrysostom on the Incomprehensible</title>
                     <incipit>Աշխատայսեր մշակք յորժամ տեսանեն ծառ անպտուղ …</incipit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Thin vellum, discoloured and creased. Size, 9" by 6". Text in two columns, each 3" wide, containing at present 25 lines of 9" in length, but cut away at the top and bottom, as well as over most of the outer column. Writing, in small square Erkat'agir, and rubrics in half uncial after the manner of 12th cent. codices. A note is written across the recto in a hand of the 15th cent., for which see under MS. Arm. f. 6., from which it was taken.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item23" n="30">
                     <locus>f. 31</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Hosea V.7-13</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum yellowed and stained. Size, 9.125" by 6.5". The fragment consists of a complete leaf. The text, surrounded by ample margins, measure 6" by 5", of 15 lines, written in elegant square Erkat'agir. Appartenly of the 12th cent. At foot of recto a peacock is drawn in brown ink. Guien by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item24" n="31">
                     <locus>f. 32</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Luke XIV.16-32</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum. Size 9.625" by 6.25". TExt in two columns (half the outer one cut away, as well as one line at top). It originally measured 9.75" by 7", of 21 lines each column. Written in Erkat'agir. Text partly mutilated. Perhaps of the 11th cent. Given by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item25" n="32">
                     <locus>f. 33</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Matt. XIVII.12 - XIX. 12, in fragments.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum, two mutilated leaves. Size, 7" by 6.75". Text in two columns, originally 21" by 7.5", of 21 lines, but now of 14 only. Written in Erkat'agir of middle size. Perhaps as early as the 11th cent. Given by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item26" n="33">
                     <locus>f. 35</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">(Recto:) Last verse of Matthew; (Verso:) Mark I.12-13 in seven lines.</title>
                     
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Wellum, much stained, 2.75" by 3.875". Text originally in two columns. Probably not later than the 11th cent. Given by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item27" n="34">
                     <locus>f. 36</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Luke XII. 19-40, XIII.22 - XIV.7, with marginal section-numbers or Ammonian canons.</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Vellum; two conjugate leaves. Size, 9.25" by 7". Text, 6.125" by 7.75", in two columns, of 24 lines each, with the outer margins cut away. Written in elegant square Erkat'agir of the 11th or 12 cent. Given by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item28" n="35">
                     <locus>f. 38</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Matt. III.13 - IV.8</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Glazed paper, much yellowed, Outer margin torn off obliquely. Size, 6" by 9.5". Text, 7.25" by 4.5", in two columns of 19 lines each. Written in a large bolorgir, of the kind current in N.W. Armenia in the 12th cent. with intermixture of uncial forms. Has red stress accents for reading aloud or intoning. Given by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
                  <msItem xml:id="MS_Arm_b_1-item29" n="36">
                     <locus>f. 39</locus>
                     <title xml:lang="en">Mark V.13-33, VII.24-28, IX.17-33, X.43-45, XIII. 2-3, XIII.8-9,11-12.</title>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <note>Glazed paper of brownish hue. Fove leaves, the forst three giving full pages, but cut across into halves, the fourth a fragment only, and the fifth the upper half of a leaf. Size, full pages, 12.5" by 8". Text, 9.25" by 6.75", in two columns, of 20 lines each. Written in bold bolorgir if the 14th cent. Given by Dr. Baronian.</note>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="mixed">
                        <extent>
                           <dimensions type="leaf" unit="in">
                              <height>19.75"</height>
                              <width>13.5"</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="1">
                           <dimensions type="line-height" unit="mm"/>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote scope="major" script="unknown"/>
                  </handDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     
                     
                  </origin>
                  <acquisition>A number of the leaves contained within this MS. were taken from other MSS. in the Bodleain collection; others were given by Dr. Baronian.</acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>Manuscript description based on: Baronian, Sukias, Rev.; Conybeare, F. C. (Frederick Cornwallis); Catalogue of the Armenian manuscripts in the Bodleain Library; Oxford, at the Clarendon Press 1918</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on presentation of a valid reader's card (for admissions procedures contact <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/services/admissions/">Bodleian Admissions</ref>). Contact <email>oriental@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email> for further information on the availability of this manuscript</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="local_class">
               <category xml:id="commentary">
                  <catDesc>Commentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supercommentary">
                  <catDesc>Supercommentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="indices">
                  <catDesc>Indices</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="translation">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="multipleWorks">
                  <catDesc>multipleWorks</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="abridgement">
                  <catDesc>Abridgement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supplement">
                  <catDesc>Supplement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="papers">
                  <catDesc>Papers</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="documents">
                  <catDesc>Documents</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="extract">
                  <catDesc>Extract</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="gloss">
                  <catDesc>Gloss</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="selection">
                  <catDesc>Selection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="diagrams">
                  <catDesc>Diagrams</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="notes">
                  <catDesc>Notes</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="letters">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="versification">
                  <catDesc>Versification</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85098523#concept">Passion Narratives (Gospels)</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh85007281#concept">Armenian Church -- Liturgy</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/sh92000686#concept">Lectionary preaching</ref>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80001460">John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407</ref>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-26">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref target="https://github.com/bodleian/armenian-mss/tree/master/processing/convertArmenian2Bodley.xsl">https://github.com/bodleian/armenian-mss/tree/master/processing/convertArmenian2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2011-05-12">
            <persName>Robin Meyer</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p93.pdf"/>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p95.pdf"/>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p97.pdf"/>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p99.pdf"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
