<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bodleian/consolidated-tei-schema/master/msdesc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="manuscript_9">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>OXFORD ARMENIAN MANUSCRIPTS CATALOGUE ONLINE</title>
            <funder>Carnegie Foundation</funder>
            <principal>Gillian Evison</principal>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Bodleian Library</publisher>
            <date calendar="#Gregorian">[Date when first made available]</date>
            <pubPlace>
               <address>
                  <addrLine>Department of Special Collections</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Bodleian Library</addrLine>
                  <street>Broad Street</street>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <postCode>OX1 3BG</postCode>
                  <addrLine>
                     <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/libraries/collections">Bodleian
                        Library</ref>
                  </addrLine>
                  <addrLine>
                     <email>specialcollections.enquiries@bodleian.ox.ac.uk</email>
                  </addrLine>
               </address>
            </pubPlace>
            <idno>OCIMCO</idno>
            <idno type="msID">MS_Arm_d_11</idno>
            <idno type="catalogue">Armenian</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc xml:id="MS_Arm_d_11" xml:lang="en">
               <msIdentifier>
                  <country>United Kingdom</country>
                  <region type="county">Oxfordshire</region>
                  <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
                  <institution>Oxford University</institution>
                  <repository>Bodleian Library</repository>
                  <collection type="main">Oriental Manuscripts </collection>
                  <idno>MS. Arm. d. 11</idno>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <summary>John Chrysostom's Commentary on Epistle to Ephesians, which is believed
                     to have been translated into Armenian from Greek in the fifth century (for more
                     on the corpus Chrysostomicum in the Armenian tradition, see Bonfiglio 2020).
                     The critical edition of this text was published in Venice in 1862 in vol. I of
                     the Commentaries on the Pauline Epistles (pp. 672-942). According to Conybeare
                     (p. 156), one of the manuscripts used for this edition was copied from the
                     present copy in Tiflis (Tbilisi) a few years before the publication (see the
                     History section). There are missing pages at the beginning and at the end of
                     the manuscript, and in its present condition, it begins with the words
                     զհրեշտակական վարս ցուցցուք (see p. 681 of the printed edition) and ends with …
                     քանզի զպատերազմաց եւ զմարտից յուշ արար, ցուցա (p. 932). According to Baronian
                     and Conybeare, there are many errors in the text: “It is particularly to be
                     remarked that there is a shuffling of large portions of the text, as on ff.
                     203-210, in the 22nd and 23rd chapters. The following is the order in which the
                     reader must there follow the text: – After f. 203b, col. I, 1. 15, չյաղթեցեր,
                     pass to f. 205b, col. II, 1. 26, եւ աստ եթէ..., as far as f. 205, col. II, 1.
                     25, եթէ որպէս. f. 209, col. I, 1. 17, մարդիկ վասն զի ... as far as f. 210, col.
                     II, 1. 25, հաստատուն կալոյ. f. 210, col. II, 1. 9, յայտնի զմեջս ... as far as
                     f. 209, col. I, 1.17, թշնամեացն շինիցէ. f. 210b, col. II, 1. 25, եւ ոչ անձին.
                     Having regard to the equal lengths of these displaced portions, it is easy to
                     see that the dislocation was produced by a transposition of folios of the
                     original copy, unnoticed by our copyist or his predecessor” (pp. 154-155). </summary>
                  <msItem xml:lang="en" xml:id="MS_Arm_d_11-item1">
                     <author key="person_41"><persName xml:lang="en">John Chrysostom, Saint,
                           -407</persName></author>
                     <title xml:lang="en" key="work_837">Commentary on Epistle to Ephesians</title>
                     <incipit xml:lang="hy" defective="true">զհրեշտակական վարս ցուցցուք </incipit>
                     <explicit xml:lang="hy" defective="true">քանզի զպատերազմաց եւ զմարտից յուշ
                        արար, ցուցա </explicit>
                     <textLang mainLang="hy">Armenian</textLang>
                     <listBibl>
                        <bibl><ref
                              target="https://archive.org/details/catalogueofarmen00bodl/page/n87/mode/2up?view=theater"
                              >Baronian, Sukias and Conybeare, Frederick C. Catalogue of the
                              Armenian manuscripts in the Bodleian Library. Oxford: Clarendon Press,
                              1918, no. 68, pp. 154-157.</ref></bibl>
                        <bibl>Bonfiglio, Emilio. “The Armenian Translations of John Chrysostom: The
                           Issues of Selection.” In Madalina Toca and Dan Batovici (eds.), Caught in
                           Translation: Studies on Versions of Late Antique Christian Literature.
                           Leiden: Brill, 2020, pp. 35-63.</bibl>
                        <bibl>John Chrysostom. Meknutʻiwn Tʻłtʻocʻn Pawłosi (Commentaries on the
                           Pauline Epistles). Venetik: S. Ghazar, 1862.</bibl>
                        <bibl>van Lint, Theo Maarten and Robin Meyer (eds.). Armenia: Masterpieces
                           from an Enduring Culture. Oxford: Bodleian Library, 2015, no 22, pp.
                           118-119.</bibl>
                     </listBibl>
                  </msItem>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <objectDesc form="codex">
                     <supportDesc material="perg">
                        <support>Vellum.</support>
                        <extent>ff. 211 <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                              <height>287</height>
                              <width>198</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </extent>
                        <collation>The quires, of 8 folios each, were originally 29 in number; there
                           are now missing the first and last ones, and one leaf after f. 16,
                           namely, the first of the second original quire. These are numbered with
                           the Armenian alphabet in the usual sequence in the middle of the lower
                           margins both of the first and last pages of each quire.</collation>
                        <condition>The manuscript is very fragile and badly damaged by humidity and
                           physical harm. The first page is nearly illegible, and ff. 1-6 have most
                           likely been perforated by a hot iron. The upper outside corners of folios
                           are discoloured by damp throughout the volume, as well as ff. 77–144. The
                           margins of ff. 39-46, as well as ff. 163-166, have been cut off with
                           scissors from top to the bottom, slightly impairing the text in some
                           places.</condition>
                     </supportDesc>
                     <layoutDesc>
                        <layout columns="2" ruledLines="26">Double columns, with large margins, of
                           26 lines each, having on an average 16 letters to the line. <dimensions
                              type="line-height" unit="mm">
                              <height>200</height>
                              <width>145</width>
                           </dimensions>
                        </layout>
                     </layoutDesc>
                  </objectDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote scope="major" script="erkatagir"><desc><label>Script: </label>The
                           writing is a small erkat‘agir or uncial letters 3 mm. high, and is
                           executed with much neatness, regularity, and uniformity. The doxologies,
                           that is, the concluding lines of the Homilies, are traced in smaller
                           characters; in these also are supplied on the margin passages omitted by
                           mistake, as on ff. 18, 56b, etc. The bolorgir form of the letter յ
                           occasionally occurs, to economise space at the end of lines: e.g. ff.
                           28b, 57, 166, etc. The orthography of the MS. is rather archaic. The
                           words are not separated. Both forms, այղ and այլ are employed, and the
                           writer does not follow any strict rule in the separation of words at the
                           end of lines, though he seems in general to try to close the line with a
                           vowel, and these vowels are charged generally with a dash on the top, as,
                           for instance, on f. 30, տարա | կուսութիւն, ապաշաւի | ցէ, փորձ ի | բաց.
                              <label>Scribe: </label><persName role="scr" key="person_103"
                              >Step‘annos</persName>.</desc></handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <decoDesc>
                     <decoNote>The MS. is embellished with several marginal ornaments (ff. 1r, 4v,
                        9v, 20v, 26r, 30r, 35r, 37v, 51v, 54v, 73r, 81r, 86r, 87v, 99r, 105v, 110v,
                        115v, 132v, 139r, 146r, 153r, 154v, 159r, 165r, 176r, 184v, 187r, 194r,
                        207r, 211r), and has two frontal vignettes inserted in the text, on ff. 123v
                        and 133r. These illuminations mark the beginnings both of chapters and of
                        the homiletic parts (յորդորակ) of the commentaries. They consist of outline
                        designs, scrolls either of simple form, or more frequently of intertwisted
                        foliations, coloured with red, green, yellow, and sometimes dark blue or
                        dark brown. The pigments employed are crude and without gradation, but
                        contrast all the more strikingly with the beauty of the writing and
                        material.</decoNote>
                  </decoDesc>
                  <bindingDesc>
                     <p>The original binding is missing. The manuscript was bound with the current
                        binding in late 19th or early 20th centuries. </p>
                  </bindingDesc>
               </physDesc>
               <history>
                  <origin>
                     <origDate calendar="#Gregorian" notBefore="1000" notAfter="1100">11th
                        cent.</origDate>
                  </origin>
                  <provenance>According to the commemorative note on f. 123r, the sponsor of the
                     manuscript was a certain Step‘anos, who could also have been the scribe of the
                     manuscript.</provenance>
                  <provenance>According to Baronian and Conybeare, “we can infer something of its
                     history from two copies preserved in the library of San Lazzaro, Venice, nos,
                     652 and 697, from which the printed edition was made. Both these copies were
                     made by Ter Nerses Sargissian, no. 697 in Tiflis in the year 1852, no. 652 in
                     Althamar. Now the former of these lacks the text comprised in the missing
                     quires of this MS., and it also has lacunae corresponding to the perforation
                     made through the first few folios of our copy (cf. Venice ed., pp. 681,
                     682,683, etc.). It moreover repeats the interchange of folios, noted above, as
                     I am informed by the librarian. Sargissian in his note points out that his
                     original was written on vellum in ergathagir. These facts prove that
                     Sargissian's original was our MS., which therefore was in Tiflis as early as
                     1852, in the possession of Ter Sahak Saharuni, son of Ter Melchised. Coming to
                     the other copy, no. 652, we know from the notice of the same scholar
                     (Sargissian), that he has copied it in 1849 in the convent of Althamar, in the
                     Lake of Van, from a MS. in bolorgir, executed in the Armenian year 1082 (A. D.
                     1632) by a scribe named Margaré. This copy is free from the imperfections at
                     the beginning and the end of our MS., but it contains the same dislocations of
                     text. The latter fact proves our MS. to have been closely related to the
                     Ałthamar copy of 1632. Yet it may be doubted if our MS. was the archetype of
                     the Aļthamar copy, for the latter here and there affords variants which can
                     hardly be attributed to the capacity of the writer Margaré: such are the words
                     հրամանք, չգոհեցի, instead of հմայք, չզինիցի of our MS. (pp. 852 and 857, ed.
                     Venice). It would appear, therefore, that our MS. and that of Althamar, both
                     derived from a common ancestor, in which the interchange of pages was found. It
                     is also probable that our MS. originated in Althamar. The excellency of the
                     writing material, the fineness of the penmanship, and the style of characters
                     all concur to show that it was made at a time when that region, namely
                     Vaspourakan, was a flourishing literary centre under the royal dynasty of
                     Ardzrounik, which came to an end in the first quarter of the 11th century” (pp.
                     156-157).</provenance>
                  <acquisition>A handwritten note under the last cover of the manuscript provides
                     information about the acquisition of the codex: “The uncial Armenian Codex of
                     Chrisostomus Commentary on St Paul’s Epistle to Ephesians was bought by me
                     [i.e., F. C. Conybeare – DZ] (Nov. 1891) for the sum of £25 from a priest of
                     the Armenian Cathedral in Tiflis by name Ciut Aghranean, who found it in the
                     house of a friend who was ignorant of its value and wished to throw it away as
                     rubbish. This former owner of it could give no account of it except that his
                     family brought it from Siunik. I owe the above particulars to S. N. Karamianz
                     of Tiflis, the cataloguer of the Armenian manuscripts in the Berlin Library.
                     Fed. C. Conybeare Oxford 1892” </acquisition>
               </history>
               <additional>
                  <adminInfo>
                     <recordHist>
                        <source>The main text of this description is from Baronian and Conybeare,
                           Catalogue of the Armenian manuscripts in the Bodleian Library, N68, pp.
                           154-157. Several additions and corrections to the text have been
                           introduced by David Zakarian for the online catalogue.</source>
                     </recordHist>
                     <availability status="restricted">
                        <p>In order to protect and preserve this artefact, access to it is
                           restricted, and readers are asked to work from reproductions and
                           published descriptions as far as possible. If you require access to the
                           original, please submit your request through the Bodleian Archives and
                           Manuscript Request service. When your request is received, you will be
                           asked to provide further information outlining the subject of your
                           research, the importance of this item to that research, and the resources
                           you have already consulted. Your application will then be considered by
                           our curatorial staff. Entry to read in the Library is permitted only on
                           presentation of a valid reader's card (for admissions procedures contact
                              <ref target="http://www.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/services/admissions/"
                              >Bodleian Admissions</ref>).</p>
                     </availability>
                  </adminInfo>
                  <surrogates><bibl type="digital-facsimile" subtype="partial"><ref
                           target="https://digital.bodleian.ox.ac.uk/inquire/p/12233893-cbda-45b9-82f7-c98f0b208082"
                              ><title>Digital Bodleian</title></ref>
                        <note>(7 selected images only)</note></bibl></surrogates>
               </additional>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="LCSH">
               <bibl>
                  <ref target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/about.html#lcsh">Library of Congress
                     Subject Headings</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="local_class">
               <category xml:id="commentary">
                  <catDesc>Commentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supercommentary">
                  <catDesc>Supercommentary</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="indices">
                  <catDesc>Indices</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="translation">
                  <catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="multipleWorks">
                  <catDesc>multipleWorks</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="abridgement">
                  <catDesc>Abridgement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="supplement">
                  <catDesc>Supplement</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="papers">
                  <catDesc>Papers</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="documents">
                  <catDesc>Documents</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="extract">
                  <catDesc>Extract</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="gloss">
                  <catDesc>Gloss</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="selection">
                  <catDesc>Selection</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="diagrams">
                  <catDesc>Diagrams</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="notes">
                  <catDesc>Notes</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="letters">
                  <catDesc>Letters</catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="versification">
                  <catDesc>Versification</catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#LCSH">
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <term target="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n80001460"
                        key="subject_n80001460">John Chrysostom, Saint, d. 407</term>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-26">
            <persName>James Cummings</persName> Up-converted the markup using <ref
               target="https://github.com/bodleian/armenian-mss/tree/master/processing/convertArmenian2Bodley.xsl"
               >https://github.com/bodleian/armenian-mss/tree/master/processing/convertArmenian2Bodley.xsl</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2012-05-28">
            <persName>Robin Meyer</persName>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <facsimile>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p153.pdf"/>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p155.pdf"/>
      <graphic url="cat_pdf/p157.pdf"/>
   </facsimile>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p><!--Body paragraph provided for validation and future transcription--></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
